<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>review on Anver Bogatov</title><link>/tags/review/</link><description>Recent content in review on Anver Bogatov</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="/tags/review/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>/reviews/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/reviews/</guid><description>Reviews of my students: Ruslan Baratov:
Translation (using Google Translate):
Anver hello !! :) Tomorrow will be my first day at work. I don't worry much, of course, because I've been going for this for a whole year. I found time for programming every day. I studied something, wrote, a lot of things were not clear and a lot of things are still not clear 😁. But I want to say thank you very much for everything.</description><content>&lt;h1 id="reviews-of-my-students">Reviews of my students:&lt;/h1>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://vk.com/rustic2">Ruslan Baratov:&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="/images/reviews/review1.png" alt="very-first-review">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Translation (using Google Translate):&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>Anver hello !! :)
Tomorrow will be my first day at work. I don't worry much, of course, because I've been going for this for a whole year. I found time for programming every day.
I studied something, wrote, a lot of things were not clear and a lot of things are still not clear 😁.
But I want to say thank you very much for everything. For what he wrote to me that day, he offered to help, it was very important for me, and that day I realized that this was a sign for me. (you can laugh about it, but it really was) 😁.
I was shocked about how you painted everything for me, everything was very competent and intelligible.
Thank you very much )
for explaining and chewing on my every question. It helped me a lot and motivated and supported me.
How many times have I started writing to you about my problem and how I just wanted to press the send button. 😀The answer immediately crossed my mind.
Plin thanks a lot the day you wrote to me, it was a defining moment for me)
And now tomorrow will be my first working day 🙂
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;hr></content></item></channel></rss>